The other day I deployed
a new feature into my vue app
and went to bed and found myself
haunted by the nightmares
that I would wake up to the app being on fire
because I accidentally introduced a new bug.
If this scenario sounds like something
you've experienced before,
we can reduce this kind of stress,
and strengthen our view apps
by using unit testing.
Unit testing is the foundation
of a well tested application.
And it might be a part of a larger testing suite
that includes snapshot testing,
and E2E, or end to end testing.
But since unit testing is the foundation,
and majority of testing we'll do,
this course will focus solely on unit testing
using just and vue test you totals.
Just is a popular jobs fair library
for actually running your tests.
And we will infuse this with the power of vue test utils.
This will allows us to test every unit
of our application
making sure that different parts of our application
are behaving like they ought to.
So what are some of the benefits
of writing unit tests?
Well first off,
we're gonna improve our code quality
because we'll deploy less bugs.
And writing components with testing in mind
means we'll end up with more isolated reasonable components.
Testing can also boost confidence
because you know that your shipping code
that actually works.
And this leads to better documentation
because a suite of unit tests
shows you how that component ought to behave.
So what exactly should we be testing?
Well, since the units of a vue app are components
we should be focusing on testing components.
So let's look at a simple example.
Let's say we have a simple component
that generates a random number.
It uses two props,
a min and max number as the range
to generate that random number
which it then renders to the DOM.
So how would we go about testing this component?
Well, it's helpful when testing
to think about the component contract.
By that I mean the agreement that this component has
about its purpose within the scope
of the larger application.
So this component's contract says
I will accept two props and use them
to generate and display a random number.
So looking at this contract
we can break this down into inputs and outputs.
The inputs are the min and max props.
And the output is that generated number
which is rendered to the DOM.
Some more inputs include
component date, props, user interaction
such as a button click.
Lifecycle methods, Vuex store,
and route params.
Outputs are things like
what is rendered to the DOM?
External function calls, events emitted by the component.
Updates to the Vuex store
and changes within child components.
So let's look at another simple example
to get more practice identifying inputs and outputs.
Here we have an appheader component.
And we have this logged in data
which determines whether we're displaying
the log out button or not.
So the data here would be considered an input.
At first this terminology might seem confusing
because unlike props,
data isn't being input into the component.
But really an input is anything that effects the output.
So if some dynamic state within our component
is considered an input.
And the output of course is going to be this button
which is either rendered or not.
So we're starting to understand what we should be testing.
But what about what we should not be testing.
We could be wasting a lot of time
testing things that we don't have to.
So looking again at this example.
We know we want to test the rendered output.
But what about the logic that actually computes that number
should we be testing this method?
The answer he is simply no,
because this is considered an implementation detail.
While it might seem counterintuitive,
with unit testing,
we're not concerned about how the component did what it did.
We just wanna know that it did what it was supposed to.
That it gave us the output that we were expecting.
By not focusing on implementation details
we won't be breaking the test
if we changed the way we were computing
that random number in the future.
Another thing we shouldn't be testing
is the Vue framework itself.
For example,
if we added some prop validation
setting these props to be of type number,
we don't have to test this validation.
We can trust NMUNST have done an awesome job
doing testing themselves.
We don't have to do their job for them.
The same goes for third-party libraries.
With this component we're using axios
to make an API call
for example,
we don't need to be testing the axios works.
We can assume that that library is well tested.
Of course if your output is dependent upon API call
we're making, we're gonna be testing that output
but we don't need to be testing Axios itself.
So now that you know about the component contract
breaking apart its inputs and outputs
and not over-testing what you shouldn't be
I'll see you in the next lesson
where we'll write our first unit test.
(gentle music)
Well,
Well, we can reduce this stress.
Well, we can reduce this --
Well, we can reduce this stress,
reduce this --
Well, we can reduce this stress.
Well we can reduce this stress and strengthen our Vue apps.
Well, we can reduce this --
well, we can reduce this stress.
I think the sirens are a bit loud.